<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://kube-green.dev/blog</id>
    <title>kube-green Blog</title>
    <updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://kube-green.dev/blog"/>
    <subtitle>kube-green Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://kube-green.dev/img/favicon.png</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing kube-green in CNCF landscape]]></title>
        <id>https://kube-green.dev/blog/cncf-landscape</id>
        <link href="https://kube-green.dev/blog/cncf-landscape"/>
        <updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are happy to announce that kube-green is now listed in the CNCF Landscape.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are happy to announce that <em>kube-green</em> is now listed in the <a href="https://landscape.cncf.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CNCF Landscape</a>.</p><p>This is an amazing achievement that makes us very proud of all the work we've been doing supporting this project.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-is-the-cncf-landscape">What is the CNCF Landscape?<a href="#what-is-the-cncf-landscape" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is the CNCF Landscape?" title="Direct link to What is the CNCF Landscape?">​</a></h2><p>For those who are not familiar with the cloud ecosystem, the <a href="https://www.cncf.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CNCF</a> — Cloud Native Computing Foundation — is "the open source, vendor-neutral hub of cloud native computing".</p><p>The goal of the CNCF is to host cloud native projects, both open source and proprietary software, in order to foster their adoption and to make cloud native universal and sustainable.</p><p>The CNCF Landscape is an interactive and curated list of all the available tools and organizations that work with cloud native technologies. Everything is organized in categories and subcategories, so that it is easier to navigate and find the right tool for every need. The Landscape is maintained by the CNCF staff: everyone is encouraged to propose open-source projects by opening a pull request to the dedicated <a href="https://github.com/cncf/landscape" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub Repository</a>.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="CNCF landscape" src="/assets/images/cncf-landscape-33c02e1305cf375cfa57db3f79c5a22a.png" width="3832" height="1908" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="kube-green-in-the-cncf-landscape"><em>kube-green</em> in the CNCF Landscape<a href="#kube-green-in-the-cncf-landscape" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to kube-green-in-the-cncf-landscape" title="Direct link to kube-green-in-the-cncf-landscape">​</a></h2><p>Starting from October 7<sup>th</sup>, <em>kube-green</em> is listed in the Scheduling &amp; Orchestration subcategory, which is part of the Orchestration &amp; Management category.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Scheduling &amp;amp; Orchestration category" src="/assets/images/cncf-landscape-category-5422c359851b2e7691698190c8dad91d.png" width="1585" height="1087" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>In the same category of Kubernetes, the <em>de facto</em> standard for orchestrating containerized application, now you can find our open-source tool that allows you to schedule when to stop unused pods.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="kube-green card" src="/assets/images/cncf-landscape-card-abc554d7a22caf45c5c59f875e42beaf.png" width="2985" height="1852" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>For example, with <em>kube-green</em> you will be able to <strong>stop all the pods of non-production environments at night-time and in non-working hours</strong>. <em>kube-green</em> takes also care of <strong>automatically restarting pods at scheduled hours</strong>, and, if needed, you can always restart any pod at any time. In this way you can <strong>save resources and money, while also reducing the carbon footprint</strong> of your infrastructure. If you want to learn more about it, read our <a href="/blog/welcome-blog-post/">Intro to <em>kube-green</em></a> and take a look at the <a href="/docs/getting-started/">documentation</a>.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="help-us-make-kube-green-grow">Help us make kube-green grow<a href="#help-us-make-kube-green-grow" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Help us make kube-green grow" title="Direct link to Help us make kube-green grow">​</a></h2><p>We strive to reach as many people as possible: the more people use <em>kube-green</em>, the more we reduce overall CO2 emissions. To do so, we need all the help we can get.</p><p>How can you contribute? There are many ways to make the difference, even for non-technical people. Here is a list of some actions you can take:</p><ul><li>Tell everyone about <em>kube-green</em>: share the repository, the website, or the CNCF card on social media and tag us;</li><li>Star the project on <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a>: let the world know how many people love this project;</li><li>Join the community and connect with other users through the <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green/discussions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub discussions</a>;</li><li>Tell us how you use <em>kube-green</em> and what you love most of it: reach out to <a href="https://github.com/davidebianchi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Davide</a> (creator of <em>kube-green</em>) or to <a href="https://github.com/akelity" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Michel</a> (Developer Advocate at <a href="https://mia-platform.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mia-Platform</a>) and tell us everything;</li><li>Improve the documentation by opening a pull request on the dedicated <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green.github.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub repository</a>;</li><li>Expand the project, adding more features or resolving any <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open issues</a>: just follow the <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">contribution guidelines</a>.</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Paolo Martinoli</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/ugho16</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="kube-green" term="kube-green"/>
        <category label="CNCF" term="CNCF"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing kube-green rebranding]]></title>
        <id>https://kube-green.dev/blog/kube-green-rebranding</id>
        <link href="https://kube-green.dev/blog/kube-green-rebranding"/>
        <updated>2022-10-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you have been one of the early adopters of kube-green you may have noticed something different in these days. New colors, new shapes, and a brand new logo? What it's all about?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you have been one of the early adopters of <em>kube-green</em> you may have noticed something different in these days. New colors, new shapes, and a brand new logo? What it's all about?
You may also be wondering if you are on the right repository, and if this is the same <em>kube-green</em> you are familiar with: don't worry, it is!
(Actually, a new version has been released: <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green/releases/tag/v0.4.1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">take a look</a> at what's new on v0.4.1).</p><p>Well, we are proud to announce that <em>kube-green</em> has gone through a full rebranding! Let's deep dive into it.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-reasons-behind-the-rebranding">The reasons behind the rebranding<a href="#the-reasons-behind-the-rebranding" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The reasons behind the rebranding" title="Direct link to The reasons behind the rebranding">​</a></h2><p>To date, <em>kube-green</em> is <strong>effectively reducing CO2 emissions since almost two years</strong>, and more and more projects are adopting <em>kube-green</em> to save energy and money. The repository has now more than 300 stars on GitHub, and it will soon be added to the <a href="https://landscape.cncf.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CNCF Landscape</a>.</p><p>We felt that <em>kube-green</em> reached the status of a <strong>mature software project</strong>, and it was the right moment to take a step further in giving it a full brand identity. We wanted the brand identity to match and reflect the maturity reached by the software, so that it will be easy to keep evolving.</p><p>So, working closely with <a href="https://github.com/Fiore17" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fiorella Cerasuolo</a>, Brand Designer at <a href="https://mia-platform.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mia-Platform</a>, we defined all the visual assets that define the new brand identity of <em>kube-green</em>.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-new-logo">The new logo<a href="#the-new-logo" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The new logo" title="Direct link to The new logo">​</a></h2><p>The greatest rebranding makeover involved the logo, that has been redesigned almost from scratch. However, it was not a disruptive revolution, but a well-reasoned evolution.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="kube-green logo concept" src="/assets/images/kube-green-logo-concept-53fdbdef8db6d0d563ce2f99d7209ce5.png" width="652" height="604" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>As the name suggests, <em>kube-green</em> works with Kubernetes. In particular, it is a Kubernetes operator that shuts down all the pods in non-production environments during non business hours. So, the logo of <em>kube-green</em> needs to evoke Kubernetes.
The previous logo recalled Kubernetes one with the seven-branched nautical helm, but for the new logo we wanted something more defined and less evident. For this reason we opted for <strong>a heptagon for the external shape</strong>: the seven sides of the polygon are a clear reference to the seven branches of Kubernetes' helm.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="kube-green new shape" src="/assets/images/kube-green-logo-helm-517be27bf97ad50fb7356eb1e1165a66.png" width="1320" height="860" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>On the background of the polygon there are <strong>two waves, representing the sea</strong>. This is another reference to the nautical theme derived from Kubernetes, together with the heptagon.
But it is also a first allusion to the main feature of <em>kube-green</em>, which is reducing CO2 pollution. In fact, the waves stand for the purity of how the open sea should be: unpolluted and uncontaminated.</p><p>At the center of the polygon there is <strong>a big green leaf</strong>, that is the worldwide recognized symbol of all the green initiatives. The leaf was the heart also of the previous logo, and we kept it also at the very center of the new logo to clearly state the main purpose of <em>kube-green</em>: helping the environment by reducing the CO2 footprint of Kubernetes clusters.
The shape of the leaf has been slightly compared with the original, to better match the new overall look and feel of the logo.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="kube-green leaf" src="/assets/images/kube-green-logo-leaf-8ae29f0e31422e55707330e8cffe533d.png" width="1320" height="860" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-new-colors">The new colors<a href="#the-new-colors" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The new colors" title="Direct link to The new colors">​</a></h2><p>The rebranding involved also the colors of <em>kube-green</em>. The <strong>green remained the main chromatic key</strong>, but we revised the adopted shades to make them more recognizable.</p><p>We opted for bright colors for two main reasons: we wanted <em>kube-green</em> to be recognized as a high-technological product, and we wanted it to stand out in the CNCF Landscape.
However, in choosing the colors, particular attention has been paid to the <strong>readability and accessibility of the logo</strong>. We made sure that the logo passed all the contrast tests, so that everyone can see it clearly.</p><p>The color palette includes three main shades: dark green, light green, and grey.
The dark green contains a little tone of blue. It is barely perceptible, but it reminds to the nautical theme of Kubernetes.
The light green is very bright: its main purpose is to give the idea of an <strong>innovative software</strong>, that leverages the latest available technologies.
The grey scale goes from the white, that acts as a definition mark between the elements of the logo, to a dark grey tending to green.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="kube-green color palette" src="/assets/images/kube-green-palette-014b55a6888d0f88653a3f20a8275f02.png" width="1506" height="1424" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>The external heptagon is colored with a seamless transition from the light green to the dark green. The gradient gives light and motion to the entire logo.
Also, the two different colors make the logo easily readable on both white and black backgrounds: this is a very important property for a software. In fact, <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>kube-green</em>'s repository</a> is hosted on GitHub, that allows users to choose between a dark and a light mode, and so does the <a href="https://kube-green.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">official website</a>.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>As you can see, there was a great effort behind this rebranding: we strive to do everything we can to make <em>kube-green</em> work better, and we believe that its success will depend also from its recognizability.</p><p>We believe that <strong>a great software needs a strong identity</strong>, and we did our best to give <em>kube-green</em> a long-lasting brand identity.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Davide Bianchi</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/davidebianchi</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="kube-green" term="kube-green"/>
        <category label="new-logo" term="new-logo"/>
        <category label="rebranding" term="rebranding"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intro to kube-green]]></title>
        <id>https://kube-green.dev/blog/welcome-blog-post</id>
        <link href="https://kube-green.dev/blog/welcome-blog-post"/>
        <updated>2022-01-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to kube-green blog!]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to <em>kube-green</em> blog!</p><p>In this blog, we'll introduce the new features of <em>kube-green</em>, and give you some other information about <em>kube-green</em>.</p><p>In this first tutorial, I will try to explain how it was born and why it is useful for reducing waste of resources.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="environmental-impact">Environmental impact<a href="#environmental-impact" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Environmental impact" title="Direct link to Environmental impact">​</a></h2><p>Everything we do online has an impact on the real world environment.<br>
<!-- -->From the emails in our inboxes to photos and videos on the cloud, from online games to digital currency, all this digital activity run on physical servers that constantly use energy.</p><p>Just some examples:</p><ul><li>minecraft all time emissions are about 600 million Kg of CO2, equivalent to drive at about 2,1 billion of km (<a href="https://www.saveonenergy.com/uk/environmental-impact-of-video-games/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">reference</a>)</li><li>bitcoin produces between 22 and 22.9 million metric tons of carbon dioxide emissions a year, or between the levels produced by Jordan and Sri Lanka (<a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/how-big-is-bitcoins-carbon-footprint-2021-05-13/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">reference</a>)</li><li><a href="https://thanks-in-advance.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a> it is possible to see how much emissions our emails generate</li></ul><p>The Kubernetes clusters are not an exception. Also if they run in a cloud provider far from us they produces CO2, also if not used.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-idea-of-kube-green">The idea of kube-green<a href="#the-idea-of-kube-green" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The idea of kube-green" title="Direct link to The idea of kube-green">​</a></h2><p>In a cluster, non production namespaces are usually used only during business hours.<br>
<!-- -->The business hours are around 40 hours per week, respect the total number of weekly hours which are 168.<br>
<!-- -->Also, in Kubernetes the resources could be allocated (both CPU and memory, setting the request of a container) also if not used. This means most of the time the pods in these namespaces are unnecessarily consuming resources.</p><p>The basic idea of <em>kube-green</em> is to stop all pods in those namespaces.  </p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="kube-green idea" src="/assets/images/idea-0ecbdfbe6704442e7d6439fa6d5df12f.png" width="2502" height="1406" class="img_ev3q"></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-it-is-possible">How it is possible?<a href="#how-it-is-possible" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How it is possible?" title="Direct link to How it is possible?">​</a></h3><p><em>kube-green</em> is a Kubernetes controller, which define a Custom Resource Definition called <em>SleepInfo</em>. <em>SleepInfo</em> CRD define when stop and restart the pods in a namespace.</p><p>So, for example in development namespaces, it is possible to stop all the pods in non business hours: wake up every morning from monday to friday and stop every night from monday to friday.</p><p>An example of <em>SleepInfo</em> CRD to make it is:</p><div class="language-yaml codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#393A34;--prism-background-color:#f6f8fa"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-yaml codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">apiVersion</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> kube</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">-</span><span class="token plain">green.com/v1alpha1</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">kind</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> SleepInfo</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">metadata</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">name</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> working</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">-</span><span class="token plain">hours</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">spec</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">weekdays</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"1-5"</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">sleepAt</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"20:00"</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">wakeUpAt</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"08:00"</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">timeZone</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token string" style="color:#e3116c">"Europe/Rome"</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#393A34"><span class="token plain">  </span><span class="token key atrule" style="color:#00a4db">suspendCronJobs</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:#393A34">:</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token boolean important" style="color:#36acaa">true</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-resources-can-you-suspend">What resources can you suspend?<a href="#what-resources-can-you-suspend" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What resources can you suspend?" title="Direct link to What resources can you suspend?">​</a></h2><p>At the time of this post, with <em>kube-green</em> at <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green/tree/v0.2.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">v0.2.0</a>, it is possible to sleep only <strong>Deployment</strong>.
Other resources will be added in the future.<br>
<!-- -->If you need some particular resources, write it in <a href="https://github.com/kube-green/kube-green/issues/77" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this issue</a> to set it in roadmap!</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2><p>Do you want to reduce the CO2 emissions and costs of your Kubernetes cluster?</p><p><a href="/docs/getting-started/">Read our documentation</a> to install <strong>kube-green</strong> in your cluster!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Davide Bianchi</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/davidebianchi</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="kube-green" term="kube-green"/>
        <category label="introduction" term="introduction"/>
    </entry>
</feed>